Guide to the Austin Foster Hawes Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Austin Foster Hawes papers
1880-1968
MS 637
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.25
(5 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, manuscripts, photographs, and newspaper clippings, which document Austin Hawes's student life, his career as state forester of Connecticut, his controversial retirement from that position, and his travels in Central and South America. Also included are papers concerning his European travels, his job as state forester of Vermont, and as professor of history at the University of Vermont. Correspondents include Henry Graves and Gifford Pinchot.
Hawes, Austin F. (Austin Foster), 1879-1962
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. E. A. Currier, ca. 1963; and Kenneth Walthall, 1996.
Scope and Contents
The Austin F. Hawes Papers contain correspondence, writings, photographs, newspaper clippings, and other papers related to Hawes's student life, his career as state forester in Connecticut and Vermont and as professor of forestry at the University of Vermont, as well as to forestry, the history of forestry in New England, and related topics.
The rather fragmentary selection of correspondence falls into two groups. The early correspondence (1900-1911) is largely in the form of typed transcripts compiled by Hawes from his letters to his family and annotated and illustrated with photographs. The letters emphasize his experiences in forestry school and in his early career rather than family matters. Some additional correspondence of this period may be found in Hawes's 1906 notebook (folder 52). The later correspondence (1942-1959) consists mostly of incoming letters discussing Connecticut forestry history; various short writings and other materials are enclosed. Prominent correspondents include Wilbur Cross, Gifford Pinchot, and Herman Chapman.
Hawes's writings, both holographs and typescripts, constitute over one-third of the papers. They deal with various aspects of forestry and the history of forestry, the major work being a two-volume typescript, "History of Forestry in Connecticut 1849-1944." Many of the writings are at least in part autobiographical. There are also two short excerpts from Hawes's diary describing trips to the Midwest (1917) and to Cuba (1938), and two notebooks. One, "Notes Taken on the Forest Conditions in Baden and Eastern France, Fall 1906," contains laid-in photographs and correspondence. The other (1912-1916) contains scattered notes on topics in forestry.
Also in the papers are memoranda and other materials of the Connecticut Forest and Park Commission, its chairman George Waldo, and Herman Chapman, president of the Commission on Forests and Wild Life, collected by Hawes. The bulk of these concern controversial changes in the administrative structure of the commission which led Hawes to resign from the commission in protest in 1943. Other materials in the papers include a few items from the Society of American Foresters; a selection of short writings by various authors, including Dorothy Canfield Fisher, on forestry and related topics; newspaper clippings; over one hundred photographs of foresters and forest scenes in Connecticut and elsewhere; memorabilia such as Hawes's certificates of appointment to the Bureau of Forestry in the Department of Agriculture, and a guestbook signed by numerous foresters; and, finally, miscellaneous papers, including a list of courses at the Yale School of Forestry, pine tree statistics from 1901, and so forth.
These papers were donated to Yale University by Mrs. E. A. Currier, sister of Austin Hawes.
Related material may be found in the Herman H. Chapman Papers, Mss Group No. 134.
Biographical / Historical
Austin F. Hawes was born on March 17, 1879, in Danvers, Massachusetts, the son of Frank M. Hawes and Harriet (Foster) Hawes. He graduated from Tufts College with a B.A. in 1901, and from the Yale School of Forestry with an M.F. in 1903. He also studied forestry in Europe in 1906. In 1908 he married Alice Clapp.
Hawes was employed by the United States Forest Service during the summers of 1900, 1901, and 1902. In 1903 he assumed the position of forest assistant, and in 1904 that of state forester of Connecticut. From 1909 to 1917 he was state forester of Vermont, and professor of forestry at the University of Vermont.
In 1921 Hawes again took up the post of state forester of Connecticut, and remained there until 1943 when he resigned in protest over the re-organization of the Connecticut Forest and Park Commission.
Hawes was the author of numerous atticles, and the co-author of several books, including Forestry in New England with R. C. Hawley (1912), Manual of Forestry for the Northeastern United States with R. C. Hawley (1918), and Common Forest Trees of Connecticut with W. R. Mattoon (1925).
Austin Hawes died in 1962.
Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; Forests and forestry -- Connecticut; Forests and forestry -- Vermont; Central America -- Description and travel; Connecticut; Foresters; Graves, Henry Solon, 1871-1951; Hawes, Austin F. (Austin Foster), 1879-1962; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory, 1899-1964
  - Correspondence, 1900-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - Selected letters (typed transcripts, compiled 1949), 1900-1904 (Box 1, Folder 7-12)
  - Selected letters: "Studying Forestry in Europe, 1906" (typed transcripts), 1906 September-November (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Writings on forestry and related topics, [1904]-1944 (Box 1, Folder 14-33)
  - Writings on forestry and related topics, [1944?]-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 34-50)
  - Diary (typed excerpts), 1917 March, 1938 March (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Notebooks:
    - "Notes Taken on the Forest Conditions in Baden and Eastern France, 1906 Fall" (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Notes on forestry and related topics, 1912-1916 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Papers of the Connecticut Forest and Park Commission, 1928-1944 June (Box 2, Folder 54-56)
  - Papers of the Connecticut Forest and Park Commission, 1944 July-1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 57-62)
  - Papers of the Society of American Foresters, 1928, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Writings of others on forestry and related topics, 1908-1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Newpaper clippings, 1899-1960 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Photographs:
    - Biltmore Forest School; Association of State Foresters; Charles Lathrop Pack; miscellaneous, 1901-1944, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Forest scenes in Connecticut and elsewhere, [ca. 1935-1940] (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Memorabilia:
    - Certificates, programs, invitations, 1901-1951 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Guestbook, 1941-1964 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Miscellaneous, 1901-1956, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
- Additional Material, 1880s-1968; Accession 1997-M-004
  - Biographical sketches, obituaries, memorial tributes, 1943, 1961-1968 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1890, 1919, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Myra D. Hawes relating to her husband, 1962-1968 (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1895, 1899-1908, 1939, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia, Circa 1880s-1962 (Box 1)
  - Notebooks, undated (Box 1)
  - Notes on Mexico and Guatemala, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, Circa 1880s-1962 (Box 1)
    - Albums
    - Central and South America (Box 1)
    - Cliff dwellings (Box 1)
    - E. Spanish America, Mexico, Guatemala, and San Salvador (Box 1)
    - Indian mounds [U.S.] (Box 1)
    - Mexico (Box 1)
    - Negatives (Box 1)
    - Personal (Box 1)
    - Scenery (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - Christmas greetings [memoirs], 1956-1962 (Box 2)
    - Notebooks [include typescripts for essays on various topics including "A Trip from Lake Atitlan, Guatemala to Oaxaca, Mexico in 1948"], Circa 1940s-1962 (Box 2)
    - On Central and South America, Circa 1940s-1950s (Box 2)
    - On forestry, Circa 1940s-1960s (Box 2)
    - On travel in Europe, Circa 1940s-1950s (Box 2)
    - On travel in the United States, Circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Printed copies, 1927-1960 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)